<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Exact journal of the victorious expedition of the confederate fleet the last year, under the command of the Right Honourable Admiral Russel giving an account of his relieving Barcellona, and the taking of a great number of prizes from the French : with a copy of a letter sent by the Algerines to congratulate the English admiral's arrival in the Mediterranean : to which is added a relation of the engagement between Catp. Killegrew, and the two French men of war that were taken in the fare of Messina.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38925</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3650</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11668</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13301800</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13301800</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98933</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38925)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98933)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 453:35)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Exact journal of the victorious expedition of the confederate fleet the last year, under the command of the Right Honourable Admiral Russel giving an account of his relieving Barcellona, and the taking of a great number of prizes from the French : with a copy of a letter sent by the Algerines to congratulate the English admiral's arrival in the Mediterranean : to which is added a relation of the engagement between Catp. Killegrew, and the two French men of war that were taken in the fare of Messina.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Whitlock ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Killigrew, James, d. 1695.</term>
               <term>Orford, Edward Russell, --  Earl of, 1653-1727.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History, Military --  1603-1714 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98933:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98933:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EXACT JOURNAL OF THE VICTORIOUS EXPEDITION OF THE <hi>Confederate Fleet,</hi> The laſt Year, under the Command of the Right Honourable Admiral <hi>RUSSEL;</hi> Giving an Account, Of his Relieving <hi>BARCELLONA,</hi> and the Taking of a great number of <hi>Prizes</hi> from the <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WITH A COPY of the LETTER ſent by the <hi>Algerines</hi> to Congratulate the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Admiral's Arrival in the <hi>Mediterranean.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which is added, A Relation of the <hi>Engagement</hi> between Capt. <hi>Killegrew,</hi> and the Two <hi>French</hi> Men of War that were taken in the <hi>Fare</hi> of <hi>Meſſina.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>I. Whitlock,</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:98933:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98933:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>IF we peruſe the Hiſtories of the Ancients, we ſhall find the <hi>Mediterranean Sea</hi> to have been the firſt moſt Eminent <hi>Neptunean</hi> Theater of Blood and Slaughter. And the ſame Stories tell us, with Aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, (for all Exceſſes are wonderful to Man) of the Naval Force of all the <hi>Perſian</hi> Empire, quite broken and deſtroyed at <hi>Artemiſium</hi> by <hi>Euribeas</hi> the <hi>Lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demonian;</hi> and at <hi>Salamine,</hi> by <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenian</hi> Admiral. Succeeding Hiſtories relate the Bloody Conteſts of the <hi>Athenians</hi> and <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> the <hi>Romans</hi> and <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> for the Dominion of the <hi>Mediterranean.</hi> Aſterwards, we hear of <hi>Auguſtus</hi> and <hi>Mark Anthony,</hi> covering the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> with Two powerful Fleets, contending for the Empire of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all the Inhabited World, till the Engagement at <hi>Actium</hi> decided the Controverſie. I might add to theſe, a diſmal proſpect of the <hi>Genoeſes</hi> and <hi>Venetian</hi> Fleets for many Years together, conteſting upon the ſame Seas for Superiority: The Two vaſt Fleets of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lym</hi> the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Sultan, and that of the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> under <hi>Don John</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> that met near the Bay of <hi>Lepanto,</hi> where the Victory, wreſted from the <hi>Infidels,</hi> within the ſpace of a few Hours, ſet at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty no leſs than <hi>13000 Chriſtian</hi> Captives. And laſtly, that Invincible <hi>Armada,</hi> with which the King of
<pb facs="tcp:98933:3"/>
               <hi>Spain</hi> then thought not only to have conquered <hi>England,</hi> but to have freighted the ſpacious Iſland it ſelf, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd it into his own Seas. But all theſe Numerous Fleets of Gallies, and Cock-boats, would have made but a ſmall Figure on that Watry Stage, had the Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent Terror of the Firſt, Second, Third and Fourth Rates, at this preſent, under the Command of Admiral <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> ſpread it ſelf among 'em. Great things are therefore expected from ſuch a prodigious Force, than which the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> never carried upon her Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders a more Formidable, ſince the <hi>Phaenicians</hi> firſt taught the Art of Sayling. No queſtion then, but a juſt and true Account of the Exploits perform'd by ſuch a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of Thunder and Lightning cannot chooſe but be acceptable to all the World. Which as we have already began to give, ſo we ſhall continue, as Occaſions offer. All that we can ſay as yet, though this be alſo very great, is only that it has ſav'd one of the moſt ſpacious Provinces of <hi>Spain</hi> from the compleat Conquest of an Inſulting E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy; and that, if any thing of Unhappineſs has hitherto attended it, 'tis only that no Oppoſition dares meet it: While <hi>Tourville,</hi> an Admiral now without a Fleet, is ſo far from preſuming to adventure an Engagement, that he does all he can to ſecure his <hi>Terribles</hi> and his <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphants</hi> with Land Fortifications; afraid to truſt 'em in their proper Elements. Fear makes him avoid the ſight of this Formidable Fleet, and Fear makes others court the Terror of it; witneſs the Submiſſive Language of the haughty <hi>Algerines</hi> to the Admiral that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands it. This I ſay, is all very great; but as greater things are expected, ſo there is no queſtion but we ſhall give the World an Account of them, the next time we appear in Print.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="journal">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98933:3"/>
            <head>A JOURNAL OF THE <hi>ENGLISH</hi> and <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TCH</hi> FLEET, Under the Command of <hi>Admiral Ruſſel.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ABOUT the end of <hi>April,</hi> in the Year 1694, the Right Honourable Admiral <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> being appointed by his Majeſty to command the Confederate Fleet, then deſign'd for the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Sea, arrived at <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> and the next Morning after his Arrival there, went on Board the <hi>Britannia.</hi> The whole Fleet which was nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merouſly formidable, was ſaid to be vittl'd for Four Months, which made moſt People conclude what was only conjectur'd
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98933:4"/>before, that ſuch great Preparations were not intended for a ſhort Expedition. For it was plainly ſeen by the Letter which the King of <hi>France</hi> ſent to the <hi>Bey</hi> of <hi>Algier,</hi> purporting, that he had order'd a Numerous Fleet of 50 Ships of Line of Battel, 20 Bomb-Veſſels, and 44 Galleys, into the <hi>Mediter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranean,</hi> to Bomb and Deſtroy all the Sea-port Towns of <hi>Spain,</hi> that would not preſerve themſelves from utter Ruin by large Contributions of Money, and to exact great Sums from <hi>Genoa</hi> and <hi>Legorn,</hi> That <hi>Tourville</hi> was to brave it in the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi> and ſhut up the Paſſages of the Streights in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that there ſhould be no Trading for either <hi>Engliſh</hi> or <hi>Dutch;</hi> and for the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> they were to be exterminated out of the Ocean. 'Twas therefore thought convenient to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the Confederate Fleet, and ſend the greateſt part of it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Admiral <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> in ſearch of this ſame Threatning Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, in order to fight the Marſhal where e're they found him, if he would ſtand the ſhock, and to keep the Seas open for free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Trade.</p>
            <p>For this purpoſe, upon the 5th of <hi>May,</hi> he ſet Sail from St. <hi>Helens,</hi> with part of the Fleet, directing his Courſe Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; the reſt of the Men of War remaining behind at the <hi>Spit-head,</hi> under the Command of Sir <hi>Cloudſly Showell,</hi> Vice-Admiral of the Red Squadron.</p>
            <p>As he ſail'd on, the Admiral had intelligence, that there lay in <hi>Bertume</hi> Road, a conſiderable Fleet of <hi>French</hi> Merchant-Men, Eaſtward bound. Upon which he ſent away Capt. <hi>Pickard</hi> in the <hi>Monmouth,</hi> together with the <hi>Reſolution</hi> and <hi>Roebuck</hi> Fire-ſhip, either to bring them away, or to deſtroy them. Accordingly upon the 10th of the ſame Month, as ſoon as it was light, they made toward the <hi>French</hi> Shore, about Seven Miles from the Fleet; and by Five a Clock in the Morning, they deſerv'd ſeveral Ships behind a Point of Land near <hi>Conquet</hi> Bay; which, immediately upon a Signal given from one of their Scouts, hois'd their Sails. In the mean time Capt. <hi>Pickard</hi> purſu'd the Man of War that was their Convoy, and forc'd her to hale in with the Shore, and run againſt the Rocks, under the Caſtle that ſtood fartheſt into the Sea. This Man of War, as the Priſoners afterwards de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98933:4"/>hapn'd to be the <hi>Jerſey</hi> Frigate, which the <hi>French</hi> had taken from the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſome time before, in the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> and which ſoon after was blown up, either by Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent or Voluntarily, 'tis not material whether. After this, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men of War ſtood into <hi>White Bay,</hi> as far as they could with ſafety, plying the <hi>French</hi> Ships that were there with their great Guns; but their Veſſels being 27 in number, all ran aſhore together, with as many more in and about <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet.</hi> The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Frigates then ſtood into <hi>Bertume</hi> Bay, and took one of the Merchants Ships, though the Caſtle ply'd them all the while with their great Shot and Bombs. There were in this Fleet Six Sloops, carrying from Ten to Sixteen Guns, two of which, as the Priſoners confeſt, were burnt by the blowing up of the <hi>Jerſey.</hi> There were alſo among them, Four Veſſels of good Burthen, part of whoſe Lading was Guns and Mortars, the biggeſt of which ran aſhore againſt the Rocks of St. <hi>Matthew</hi>'s Point. The Merchants Ships were in all about 55 Sail, of which 35 were either burnt or ſunk, 25 in <hi>White-Bay,</hi> 4 on the South-ſide of the Point of the Bay, and 6 on the South-ſide of <hi>Conquet,</hi> their Lading being for the moſt part Salt, Wine and Brandy. The News of this Exploit ſo luckily perform'd, came to <hi>Whitehall</hi> by an Expreſs dated from the Fleet, the 18th of <hi>May.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By another Expreſs dated the 19th of the ſame Month, an Account was given, That Capt. <hi>Townſend</hi> in the <hi>Foreſight,</hi> and Capt. <hi>Cooper</hi> in the <hi>England</hi> Frigate, having Four <hi>Engliſh</hi> Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vateers in their Company, upon the 17th, about Six a Clock in the Morning, to the Eaſt-ward of Cape <hi>la Hogue,</hi> got ſight of another Fleet of <hi>French</hi> Merchants, bound for <hi>Diep</hi> and <hi>Dunkirk;</hi> and giving them Chaſe, tack'd upon Five of them, one of which happened to be a Man of War of 23 Guns, and ran them all aſhore, in a Rocky Place, call'd <hi>Omonvel,</hi> where they were protected by a ſmall Caſtle. Upon which they made after the reſt of the Fleet, and forc'd ſeveral of them aſhore near <hi>Sherburg;</hi> and while they kept off the <hi>French</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Privateers took Six of them: The whole Fleet conſiſting of about 50 Sail, laden with Corn and Bread for the ſervice of the <hi>French</hi> Army in <hi>Flanders.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:98933:5"/>
            <p>This firſt motion of part of the Confederate Fleet, was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to obſerve the Countenances of the <hi>French</hi> in <hi>Breſt,</hi> and to get the beſt intelligence that could be had, what Strength they had left behind in the Ocean; for that the Admiral did not ſail from S. <hi>Helens</hi> till the 29th of <hi>May</hi> in the Morning, at what time there being but little Wind, and that which was being againſt him, he was forced to come to an Anchor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; but at length upon the 30th in the Morning, the Wind choping about to the North with a freſh Gale, the whole Fleet ſet ſail, and before Noon of the ſame day, were quite out of fight.</p>
            <p>'Tis ſaid, that the whole Fleet, <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch,</hi> conſiſted of 48 Sail, or 56, as was ſaid by others; particularly that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fleet was compoſed of 3 Firſt Rates, the <hi>Britannia,</hi> the <hi>Sovereign,</hi> and the St. <hi>Andrew;</hi> 6 of the Second, 18 of the Third, 6 of which carried 80 great Guns apiece; 6 of the Fourth, 2 of the Fifth, 6 of the Sixth, together with 9 Fire-Ships: which were to be reinforced by 23 Sail more, that lay at <hi>Cadiz,</hi> and to be farther alſo joyn'd by the Men of War, and Galleys of <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean time, <hi>Nouailles</hi> being ready to take the Field in <hi>Catalogna, Tourville</hi> was ſent down to <hi>Toulon,</hi> to haſten out the <hi>French</hi> Fleet with all the ſpeed imaginable; and he was ſo quick, that he was got with a Squdron of Men of War in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Road of <hi>Toulon,</hi> and was ready to ſet Sail. But upon the 9th of <hi>May,</hi> ſo violent a Storm, attended with Thunder and Lightning, aroſe in thoſe Parts, that the Admirals Ship; and Two more, were ſo much endamag'd in their Maſts, that it was the 14th before he could put to Sea, in order to joyn the Galleys, and ſo ſet fayl together towards the Coaſts of <hi>Catalogna,</hi> where he was to aſſiſt with his Bombs from the Sea, while the <hi>French</hi> attacked the Sea-port Towns of that Province by Land. To that purpoſe, he ſail'd away with the Galleys from <hi>Marſeilles,</hi> to the Bay of <hi>Roſes,</hi> where he was joyn'd by <hi>Chaſteau Renaut,</hi> with a Squadron from <hi>Breſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98933:5"/>
            <p>And now the <hi>French</hi> carri'd all things before them in <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogna; Tourville</hi> rode Triumphant at Sea, and <hi>Nouailles,</hi> Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious by Land; had won <hi>Palamos</hi> and <hi>Gironne,</hi> and there was no queſtion but that <hi>Barcellona</hi> would have been the next that would have been Beſieg'd; which ſeem'd indeed to be the principal Deſign of that Campaign. But the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings that Admiral <hi>Ruſſel</hi> was approaching toward the <hi>Streights,</hi> quite alter'd the Meaſures of the <hi>French;</hi> ſo that <hi>Tourville</hi> inſtead of ſailing from <hi>Palamos</hi> to <hi>Barcellona</hi> according to his Firſt Orders, was directed to return to <hi>Toulon,</hi> with all the haſt he could. And indeed 'twas a lucky Eſcape for the <hi>French</hi> Admiral, who got into <hi>Toulon</hi> but the 4th of <hi>July;</hi> whereas Admiral <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> as the Letters from <hi>Marſeilles</hi> at that time confirm'd, appear'd at the heighth of <hi>Barcellona</hi> the 7th.</p>
            <p>However it were, it was not to be imagin'd, that the Confederate Fleet, which could ſail no faſter than the Wind could carry them along, and of whoſe Motion the <hi>French</hi> Court was able to give more ſpeedy Intelligence, and as much as was neceſſary for <hi>Tourville</hi>'s Preſervation, more conveniently than the Admiral could haſten to prevent it; for theſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, I ſay, it was not to be imagin'd, that the Confederate Fleet could eaſily ſurprize the <hi>French.</hi> After the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral had weigh'd, and ſet forward from St. <hi>Hellens,</hi> there was little or no News heard of him; only that he was ſeen to paſs at a diſtance by <hi>Dartmouth</hi> and <hi>Plimouth</hi> the 5th of <hi>June;</hi> and that upon the Ninth at Night, the <hi>Alliance</hi> Packet-Boat bound from <hi>Corona</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> in her Voyage to <hi>Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> diſcover'd a great number of Lights to the South Weſt of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſhant,</hi> which he judg'd to be the Fleet under Admiral <hi>Ruſſel.</hi> To which we may add the Report of the Maſter of another Veſſel which put into <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> and about the ſame time, brought Advice, that he met Admiral <hi>Ruſſel</hi> in the heighth of <hi>Lagos,</hi> in <hi>Portugal,</hi> ſteering toward the <hi>Streights</hi> with a favourable Wind. So that after it was heard, that he had doubled the Cape of St. <hi>Vincent,</hi> between <hi>Lisbon</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diz,</hi> the firſt Expreſs that came from him, and was received at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> was dated on Board the <hi>Britannia,</hi> the firſt of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98933:6"/>
               <hi>July,</hi> Old Stile, off of <hi>Tangier,</hi> wherein the Admiral gave an Account that he had not ſo much as touch'd at <hi>Cadiz,</hi> but that he had ſent Orders to Rear Admiral <hi>Nevil,</hi> who rode in that Bay, with a Squadron of <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Men of War, to joyn him to the Weſtward of Cape <hi>Spartel;</hi> which they accordingly did on the 30th of <hi>June.</hi> Farther, that when thoſe Letters were written, he was haſtning with all the ſpeed he could toward <hi>Barcellona,</hi> being inform'd that the <hi>French</hi> Fleet lay between that Place and <hi>Alfagues.</hi> That he had likewiſe order'd the <hi>Turkey</hi> Ships both <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch,</hi> together with the Men of War appointed for their Convoy, to make the beſt of their way to <hi>Cartagena,</hi> and there to ſtay for ſuch farther Orders which he ſhould ſend them from <hi>Alicant,</hi> according to the Intelligence which he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of the Enemy.</p>
            <p>Upon the 13th of <hi>July,</hi> the ſame welcom News was ſent by an Expreſs from <hi>Cadiz</hi> to <hi>Madrid,</hi> where the Tydings were joyfully received in the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Court, that Admiral <hi>Ruſſel</hi> had paſſed by that Harbour with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleet toward the <hi>Streights,</hi> having ſent in a ſmall Frigate before, with Orders to Rear Admiral <hi>Nevil,</hi> to joyn him near Cape <hi>Spartel.</hi> This Frigate arriv'd at <hi>Cadiz</hi> the 8th of the ſame Month, and the next Morning the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron, together with Ten Spaniſh Men of War which lay in that Bay, ſail'd away all together with a fair Wind. And now fearleſs of Moleſtation, divers Satees and other ſmall Veſſels were order'd from <hi>Cadiz,</hi> Port St. <hi>Mary,</hi> and St. <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car,</hi> freighted with above 2000 Souldiers and Sea-men, for the Succour of <hi>Barcellona,</hi> to <hi>Malaga;</hi> where lay Six Galleys ready to convoy them, with Sixteen more that were gon before to <hi>Cartagena,</hi> in expectation of others that were to joyn them, which being joyn'd, would make Twenty Eight in all, and were to attend the main Fleet, or at leaſt the greateſt part of them.</p>
            <p>Upon the 23d of <hi>July,</hi> an Expreſs from <hi>Gibraltar,</hi> brought News to the Court at <hi>Madrid,</hi> that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Squadron commanded by Rear Admiral <hi>Nevil,</hi> and the Ten <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Men of War, had joyn'd Admiral <hi>Ruſſel</hi> upon the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98933:6"/>10th and 11th of the ſame Month near <hi>Tangier;</hi> at what time the whole Fleet was ſtop'd by a ſtrong <hi>Levant,</hi> till the 15th; when the Wind chopping about to the Weſt, they paſt through the <hi>Streights</hi> the ſame day, ſteering their Courſe toward <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellona.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the 17th of <hi>July,</hi> Capt. <hi>Banks</hi> in the <hi>Carſlile</hi> Frigate, with Four Ketches, was ſent to <hi>Malaga,</hi> to ſetch freſh Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions for the Fleet, which he rejoyn'd the next day, ſtill directing its courſe for <hi>Barcellona:</hi> For the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Admiral thought it not convenient to come in ſight of <hi>Malaga,</hi> but paſs'd by it the ſame day that he ſent Capt. <hi>Banks</hi> thither, keeping more to the Shore of <hi>Barbary.</hi> All this while no <hi>French</hi> Fleet appear'd; only Six of their Men of War were ſeen off <hi>Almeria,</hi> upon the 13th, where they would have had Proviſions for their Money, but it was refus'd them; they being ſuppos'd to be Scouts ſent forth to get intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of the Confederate Fleet. In the mean time, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Merchants Ships bound for <hi>Turkey</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> under the Convoy of Five Men of War, proceeded unmoleſted in their Voyages.</p>
            <p>On the 8th of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> Admiral <hi>Ruſſel</hi> arrived before <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellona</hi> with the whole Fleet, conſiſting of about 140 Sail, of which 88 were Ships of Line. He had met with ſeveral Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mora's, occaſion'd by contrary Winds, which render'd the Voyage ſomewhat Tedious, though every Moment were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd to haſten it. Of this Marſhal <hi>Novailles</hi> gave the King of <hi>France</hi> advice, by an Expreſs from his Camp at <hi>Blaines,</hi> (not far from <hi>Barcellona</hi>) adding withal, that while Admiral <hi>Ruſſel</hi> anchor'd before the City, Two and Twenty of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Galleys came before the Place; and making in as cloſe to the Shore as they could, Canonado'd the <hi>French</hi> Troops that were poſted near the Shoar.</p>
            <p>Admiral <hi>Ruſſel</hi> continu'd before <hi>Barcellona</hi> with the whole Fleet riding in Three Lines, from the 8th to the 26th, at what time he weigh'd, and the next day appear'd before <hi>Blaines,</hi> which is about Four Leagues from <hi>Palamos.</hi> And there was no queſtion but the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Admiral would have been glad that Marſhal <hi>Tourville</hi> would have tarry'd for his coming. But
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98933:7"/>upon the News of his Approach to the <hi>Streights,</hi> or, at leaſt, of his having paſs'd the <hi>Streights,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Admiral inſtead of Sailing to <hi>Barcellona</hi> to aſſiſt <hi>Nouailles</hi> in the Siege of that Place, according to his firſt Orders, made a ſpeedy return to <hi>Toulon,</hi> and was ſo early in his Retreat, that he enter'd that Port upon the 4th of <hi>July.</hi> And ſuch was his fear of being aſſayl'd in the Harbour, that he ſent away ſome part of the Galleys to <hi>Marſeilles,</hi> and moor'd the reſt before his Men of War for their better Security: And more than this, he took out the great Guns out of the great Men of War, to make Batteries upon the Shore; for the raiſing of which, his Men wrought Day and Night, and of which he try'd the firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and how far they were able to annoy an Aſſayling Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, after they were finiſh'd. He alſo caus'd the biggeſt of his Ships to be hail'd within the Caſtles. He alſo caus'd ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Pieces of Canon to be planted upon the Iſlands near <hi>Marſailles.</hi> And ſtill for the ſecurity of the great Ships at <hi>Toulon,</hi> he order'd moreover a ſtrong Chain and a Boom to be laid croſs the Entrance of the Port. Nor was all this thought ſufficient, till beſides all theſe Precautions, he had rais'd a New Fort, which was call'd <hi>Fort Tourville,</hi> to defend the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the Haven.</p>
            <p>This was a ſign, that the <hi>French</hi> Admiral lay under great Apprehenſions of Danger; and yet in the midſt of theſe fears, it was then reported, that <hi>Tourville</hi> held a Council of War, wherein it was debated, whether he ſhould put to Sea and fight the Confederate Fleet, upon an Imagination that the Sea-men were tyr'd out with the length of their Voyage, and Sickly; upon which Suppoſitions, he thought there might be ſome Advantage gain'd. But it was carri'd in the Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, all the Officers alledging, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> were no freſh-water Souldiers, and therefore that it would be a Madneſs to engage ſo formidable a Fleet. However it was at the ſame time confirm'd, that the whole Coaſt of <hi>Provence</hi> was in a great Conſternation, and that the Inhabitants of the Sea-Towns carry'd away the beſt of their Goods up higher in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Country, for fear of being Bomb'd in their Houſes. The Court of <hi>France</hi> alſo was not a little miſtruſtful of their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98933:7"/>own Sea-men; and therefore fearing leaſt the Officers and Sea-men belonging to the Galleys ſhould play their Officers a ſcurvy Trick upon the appearing of the Confederate Fleet upon the Coaſts of <hi>Provence,</hi> remitted to <hi>Marſailles</hi> an Hundred Thouſand Livres, for the payment of part of their Wages, thereby to engage them to ſtand firm in their Duty.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, there was great Joy in the Court of <hi>Madrid,</hi> to hear of the Arrival of the Confederate Fleet upon the Coaſts of <hi>Spain.</hi> The King particularly, as a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of his great ſatisfaction, ſent a Preſent of a Jewel to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Admiral, valued at Five and Twenty Thouſand Crowns, and another to Vice Admiral <hi>Calenberg,</hi> valued at Twelve Thouſand.</p>
            <p>When the Confederate Fleet arriv'd in the Bay of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellona,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Eſcalona,</hi> Viceroy of <hi>Catalogna,</hi> went on Board the <hi>Britannia,</hi> to Compliment the Admiral, and during their Interview, all the Canon of the Fleet, and the City, were diſcharg'd Three times. The next day Admiral <hi>Ruſſel</hi> went Aſhore to repay the Viceroy his Viſit; who received him with all the Honour and Reſpect that was due to his Perſon. After a Conference of a little more than an Hour, there was held a Council of War; at the Concluſion of which, the Admiral return'd to his Ship. The Viceroy alſo ſent him as a Preſent, a Hundred and Fifty Sheep, Four Calves, Six Hundred Candles of Virgins Wax, Six Hundred Tallow Candles, Six Hundred Pound of Choco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, One Thouſand Six Hundred Pound of Sugar, a great number of Capons, Pullets and Turkies, a great quantity of Pulſe, and all ſorts of Fruits, a Hundred Barrels of Excellent Wine, and proportionably of other Liquors, with a proportionable quantity of Snow to cool his Wine. The Magiſtracy alſo of <hi>Barcellona</hi> made him a Preſent of Two <hi>Barbary</hi> Horſes richly harneſſed, to the value of Three Hundred Piſtoles.</p>
            <p>And now to return to the Courſe of the Confederate Fleet, Admiral <hi>Ruſſel</hi> having ſtay'd before <hi>Barcellona</hi> from the 8th to the 26th of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> ſet ſail from thence the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98933:8"/>ſame Day, no body knowing what Courſe he intended to ſteer; only that he proceeded as ſar as <hi>Blanes,</hi> Four Leagues beyond <hi>Barcellona,</hi> as the Letters from <hi>Toulon</hi> ſignified. For Mounſieur <hi>Tourville</hi> no ſooner heard of Admiral <hi>Ruſſel</hi>'s leaving <hi>Barcellona,</hi> but he ſent out ſeveral light Frigates to get intelligence of his Motions; but whether it were that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Admiral was well inform'd that the <hi>French</hi> Fleet was too ſtrongly Barricado'd up in the Port of <hi>Toulon,</hi> to be attack'd without time and leiſure, or that perhaps he had not then received his Orders to winter in the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diterranean;</hi> and therefore finding the Seaſon far ſpent, thought it high time to return back into the Ocean, he ſteer'd back again for the <hi>Streights,</hi> and upon the 5th of <hi>September,</hi> paſs'd by <hi>Alicant,</hi> with a fair Wind; and the next Day in the Afternoon, the whole Fleet paſs'd by <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagena,</hi> with the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Men of War, the Gallies only being order'd back to <hi>Cartagena;</hi> and upon the 15th he came before <hi>Malaga.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean time, the <hi>French</hi> Admiral meditated Two Deſigns, either to ſlip by the Confederate Fleet, and get before Admiral <hi>Ruſſel</hi> with the Squadrons of <hi>Breſt,</hi> into the <hi>Atlantick</hi> Ocean, while the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> were buſied in the more diſtant part of <hi>Provence;</hi> for there was a Rumour ſpread abroad, of an intended Bombing of <hi>Nice,</hi> or elſe to watch the return of the Fleet to the <hi>Streights,</hi> and ſail away a ſecond time for <hi>Barcellona,</hi> where <hi>Nouailles</hi> lay ready, together with ſuch new Succours as he ſhould bring him, to finiſh the Conqueſt of <hi>Catalogna.</hi> The firſt he had received Orders at one time to attempt, when Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral <hi>Ruſſel</hi> cover'd <hi>Barcellona;</hi> but upon better Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, the Court of <hi>France</hi> not finding it feaſible to get by a watchful Enemy without being encounter'd, diſcharg'd him of thoſe Cares.</p>
            <p>As to the ſecond, ſo ſoon as Admiral <hi>Ruſſel</hi>'s Back was turn'd, and while there was yet no certainty of Admiral <hi>Ruſſel</hi>'s wintring in the <hi>Mediterranean, Nouailles</hi> and <hi>Tourville</hi> were in great hopes, that they together, might carry <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celona</hi> before the end of the Campaign; and the Court of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98933:8"/>
               <hi>France</hi> flatter'd her ſelf with the ſame Expectations. <hi>Tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville</hi> therefore having ſent before Seven or Eight Men of War, and ſome Fiteſhips, under the Command of Monſieur <hi>Beaujeu,</hi> on which were embark'd ſeveral Regiments, ſet ſail with the reſt of the Fleet for the Coaſt of <hi>Catalogna.</hi> The News of this ſayling of the <hi>French</hi> Fleet, carrying with it ſome Thouſands of Land Souldiers for the Rein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcement of <hi>Nouailles,</hi> and the Marching thither at the ſame time of a conſiderable Body of <hi>French</hi> Horſe by Land, made all People believe that ſome great Enterprize was to be undertaken on that ſide, and that the Siege of <hi>Barcelona</hi> was reſolv'd upon. About the ſame time alſo, Three <hi>French</hi> Men of War, of Sixty and Seventy Guns, appeared off of <hi>Alicant,</hi> attended by a Fireſhip, which gave a ſuſpicion of a greater Number. All theſe things put together, brought Admiral <hi>Ruſſel</hi> again into <hi>Alicant</hi> Road, where he caſt Anchor upon the 20th of <hi>September,</hi> New Stile: Of which when the <hi>French</hi> were inform'd, and moreover that it was reſolv'd that the Confederate Fleet ſhould winter in the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> new Orders were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch'd away from Court to the Marſhal, which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived juſt as he was beginning to land his Men at <hi>Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos</hi> and <hi>Blanes;</hi> ſo that he was forced to return again with all the ſpeed he could to <hi>Toulon,</hi> where he arrived the 23d of <hi>September,</hi> having ſcap'd Two very terrible Storms, one at his ſetting out, which brought him again into Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to repair the Maſts and Rigging of ſeveral Men of War; the ſecond at his Return, which ſcatter'd his Ships, though they all rejoyn'd at length, except one large Man of War, which had ſeveral Companies of Souldiers A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board, and a Fly-boat laden with Bombs and Mortars. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which diſappointment and ill ſucceſs, they fell to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigging their Ships, the whole Fleet being order'd to be laid up.</p>
            <p>While Admiral <hi>Ruſſel</hi> lay in the Road of <hi>Alicant,</hi> he was taken ill of a Fever; but after he had been ſome days aſhore in that City, was perfectly reſtor'd to his Health, and return'd Aboard the Fleet, a conſiderable Squadron
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98933:9"/>of which had however been cruiſing as far as <hi>Minorca,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Command of Vice Admiral <hi>Aylmer,</hi> to ſee if he could get ſight of the <hi>French.</hi> But hearing no News of the Enemy, he came to an Anchor again in the ſame Road the 2d of <hi>October.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Much about the ſame time, Six <hi>Dutch</hi> Privateers as they were Cruiſing not far from the Iſland of <hi>Maltha,</hi> came up with Two <hi>French</hi> Men of War, the one of Sixty, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Forty Four Guns, having Four Merchants Ships richly laden from <hi>Smyrna</hi> under their Convoy; upon which the Privateers attack'd the Two Men of War, and ſo rudely handl'd the biggeſt, that ſhe was forced to bear a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way for <hi>Maltha</hi> to ſave her ſelf; but the Privateers took the other, together with the Four Merchant Men. At the ſame time alſo Three <hi>Zealand</hi> Privateers cruiſing near <hi>Sicily,</hi> took a <hi>French</hi> Frigate of Eighteen Guns, and an Hundred and Ten Men, on Board of which, they found Ten Thouſand Pieces of Eight in ready Money. And while one of the Privateers guarded the Prize to <hi>Palermo,</hi> the other Two met Three <hi>French</hi> Men of War, of Sixty and Forty Guns, which they fought ſeveral Hours, till Night parted them.</p>
            <p>This quick Return of Marſhal <hi>Tourville</hi> to <hi>Toulon,</hi> upon Admiral <hi>Ruſſel</hi>'s ſayling back to <hi>Alicant,</hi> was in ſome meaſure ridicul'd by the <hi>French</hi> themſelves, as appear'd by a Letter written from <hi>Paris,</hi> upon occaſion of <hi>Tourville</hi>'s Retreat, to this effect.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:98933:9"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE quick Return of our Fleet to</hi> Toulon, <hi>gives occaſion to various Diſcourſes; what the Succeſs was, is publickly known: The Managers only feel the Thorns of it. We ſhall have neither any Engagement, nor any Siege of</hi> Barcellona <hi>this Year: 'Twas not thought convenient to hazard the one, nor attempt the other. Yet all things ſeem'd to tend to a Tryal of theſe Two Events. The Departure of the whole Fleet, and the Expence of ſetting it out, with Bomb Galliots and Mortars, ſhew'd that there was ſomething elſe intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, than a bare Landing of Men; nor did they ſend their Horſe by Land, to go up the Hill, and ſo come down again. Yet all are returned or returning, both Fleet and Cavalry. Whatever the Reaſons were, the Campaign is now at an end, and the Court are at their Wits end, what Courſe to take with the Fleet, whoſe lying ſtill, or doing nothing to the purpoſe, is laught at in all the Courts of</hi> Europe.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>When it was that Admiral <hi>Ruſſel</hi> receiv'd his Orders from <hi>England</hi> to Winter in the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> is not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial. Certain it is however, that when he underſtood that the Marſhal was gone back, and that the intended At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon <hi>Barcellona</hi> was given over, he ſet ſail from the Road of <hi>Alicant</hi> upon the Fifth of <hi>October,</hi> ſending away the <hi>Greyhound</hi> Frigate to the Bay of <hi>Gibralter,</hi> with Orders to ſuch <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men of War as lay there, to joyn him at Cape <hi>Spartell,</hi> where he intended to cruiſe for ſome time, in order to meet the <hi>French,</hi> in caſe they ſhould attempt to paſs the <hi>Streights.</hi> This was written from <hi>Malaga;</hi> and other Letters dated the 12th of <hi>October</hi> from <hi>Cadiz,</hi> affirm'd, in Confirmation of the former Intelligence, that the whole Fleet under the Command of Admiral <hi>Ruſſel,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:98933:10"/>appear'd in the ſight of that Port the ſame Day; and that at the ſame time alſo an Hundred Sail of Ships from <hi>England,</hi> with Proviſions and other Neceſſaries for the Fleet, under the Convoy of ſeveral Men of War, arriv'd in that Port.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, it was confirm'd on all Hands by freſh Intelligence, that the <hi>French</hi> were unrigging all their Men of War at <hi>Toulon,</hi> except Six, who were to Cruiſe during the Winter; and that the Sea-men of the Weſtern Provinces, were to return back by Land to <hi>Breſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding thoſe Confirmations, Admiral <hi>Ruſſd</hi> careful to avoid all Surpriſes of the <hi>French,</hi> under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of unrigging their Ships, though he appear'd before <hi>Cadiz</hi> upon the 12th of <hi>October,</hi> yet kept off at Sea for ſeveral Days; nor was it till the 17th, that he came to Anchor in the Bay of the ſame Place, after he had le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Men of War to cruiſe in the Streights. All this while, notwithſtanding the Rumours ſpread abroad by the <hi>French,</hi> to leſſen the Fears of the People, that there was a great Mortality, and want of Proviſions in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleet, and that they had loſt one third part of their Men, the whole Fleet continued Healthy, and in a good Condition, as being all along carefully pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided with all things neceſſary, both as to the Men and Ships.</p>
            <p>At length however, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Admiral who lay ready to ſail, in order to cruiſe about the <hi>Streights</hi> Mouth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſur'd that the <hi>French</hi> were in earneſt as to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigging their Ships, and that there was no fear of their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any farther Attempts that Seaſon, he took up his ſtation in the Bay of <hi>Cadiz,</hi> about the beginning of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember;</hi> where he firſt gave order for the Cleaning and Careening of the ſmaller Ships with all the ſpeed that poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly could be, in order to their Cruiſing, intending after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>words to do the like by the Great ones. In the mean time, the Duke of <hi>Seſta,</hi> Captain General of <hi>Andaluſia,</hi> and <hi>Don Franciſco de Velaſco,</hi> Governour of <hi>Cadiz.</hi> went
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98933:10"/>ſeveral times on Board the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Admiral, to pay him their Reſpects; which Viſits of his, the Admiral repay'd with equal Civility. 'Twas alſo ſaid, that His Catholick Majeſty had engag'd to pay five Hundred Thouſand Crowns toward the Expences of the Confederate Fleet in the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> and that Aſſignments had been already receiv'd for a good part of the Sum.</p>
            <p>In this ſame Poſture of Affairs, the main Buſineſs now was to keep ſome Men of War always in a readineſs to prevent all ſiniſter Events, and to ſend forth other Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates upon the ſcout, to diſcover what Ships the Enemy had Abroad, and for the preſervation of the Merchants Trade. And this continual Cruiſing of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch,</hi> had ſuch good ſucceſs, that the Commerce of the <hi>French</hi> received conſiderable Interruption almoſt every day. About the 20th of <hi>October,</hi> were brought into <hi>Cadiz,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thoſe already mentioned, a <hi>French</hi> Man of War of Twenty Four Guns. and an <hi>Algerine,</hi> having on Board Two Hundred <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Paſſengers, with a great many Preſents for the <hi>Grand Seignor,</hi> the whole being valued at Four Hundred Thouſand Pieces of Eight. Captain <hi>Cornwall</hi> in the <hi>Adventure,</hi> took Two <hi>French</hi> Prizes as they were ſayling through the <hi>Streights</hi> Mouth, bound from <hi>Marſeilles</hi> to <hi>Lisbon,</hi> very richly laden with Silks and other valuable Commodities, and brought them into <hi>Cadiz</hi> upon the 30th of <hi>September.</hi> Capt. <hi>Watton</hi> in the <hi>Lark,</hi> took a <hi>French</hi> Prize laden with Fiſh from <hi>Newſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and carri'd her into the ſame Port, upon the 9th of <hi>October.</hi> The <hi>Mary Galley</hi> and <hi>Grey-hound,</hi> carried in another Prize upon the 12th, bound from <hi>Lisbon</hi> to <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeilles;</hi> and the ſame day the <hi>Portſmouth Galley</hi> arriv'd at <hi>Cadiz,</hi> with Two <hi>French</hi> Satee's bound from <hi>Sally</hi> to <hi>Marſeilles.</hi> About the middle of <hi>December,</hi> the <hi>Dragon</hi> took a <hi>French</hi> Man of War that carri'd Thirty Six Guns, and Two Hundred Men, call'd the <hi>Spheare,</hi> upon the Coaſt of <hi>Portugal,</hi> and ſail'd away with his Prize to <hi>Cadiz.</hi> So that the Damage which the <hi>French</hi> ſuſtain'd by the Cruiſing of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch,</hi> in the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98933:11"/>
               <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Seas, was no leſs than the loſs of Nineteen Prizes, among which were Seven Merchant-Men richly laden, and all this before the end of <hi>November.</hi> Nor muſt we omit another very Rich Ship, bound from <hi>Marſeilles</hi> to <hi>Smyrna,</hi> ſaid to be worth ſeveral Hundred Thouſand Pieces of Eight, which was taken about the beginning of <hi>January,</hi> by Two <hi>Dutch</hi> Privateers that cruis'd about <hi>Maltha.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Toward the latter end of <hi>January,</hi> the Letters from <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diz</hi> gave an Account, that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> were diligently preparing to get their Men of War ready to joyn the Confederates, who by that time had Careen'd the greateſt part of the Fleet; Admiral <hi>Ruſſel</hi> all the while reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both Souldiers and Sea-men under the Severity of an exact Diſcipline, and was become ſo Formidable in the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> that the <hi>Divan</hi> of <hi>Algier,</hi> thought it high time to court him; and to that purpoſe ſent the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Letter.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:98933:11"/>
                  <head>The Vice-Governour <hi>Ibrahim E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandi,</hi> and all the <hi>Divan,</hi> to the Renowned Admiral, and Valiant General <hi>Ruſſel,</hi> our Dear and Well-beloved and Faithful Friend, ſo well eſteemed alſo by that Chriſtian King, whoſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom may it be always prudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly govern'd, Greeting.</head>
                  <p>WE write this Letter to you, proteſting that 'tis impoſſible to expreſs our Friendſhip for you, nor to utter it in our Words. We beſeech the Almighty God, that your Enemies and ours, may be reduced to that Extremity, that they may be always unable to withſtand your Power. And it is our Deſire, that the Friendſhip which is between us, may every manner of way increaſe. God be praiſed, for that this Year you are come into the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Sea, to our great Joy. The Ship, which you ſent us, is happily arrived in this Port, and the Captain, who is at your Service, together with the Conſul, who in all Places, and upon all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, loudly ſpeak your Fame, have delivered the Letter which you wrote to us and the <hi>Divan,</hi> wherein we find Aſſurances of your own, and the Friendſhip of your great King: Upon which, we caus'd all the Canon of our Caſtle
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98933:12"/>to be diſcharg'd, to the great joy of thoſe that love us, and the terror of our Enemies. We are aſſured, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> are the beſt Friends we have, and we beſeech God to preſerve both them and us from all Evil. We were extreamly overjoyed at the ſight of theſe Ships, and we ſhall take great delight to behold them, as often as your Affairs will permit. We admir'd the Prudence and Conduct of your Captain, in the Proofs which he gave of his good With, and in his whole manner of Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; but we were not in a capacity to ſhew him that kindneſs which he merited. Our Thrice Fortunate Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor and Maſter is now beſieging <hi>Tunis,</hi> with Thirty Thouſand Men, which is the Reaſon of his Abſence, and which we beg of you not to take in ill part; for ſo ſoon as it pleaſes God that he returns Victorious, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> will have no reaſon to be diſſatisfied with the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of his Friendſhip. You likewiſe give us to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that your Maſter has granted our Deſires, in ſetting Mr. <hi>Cole,</hi> a Perſon well known to us, to be his Agent and Conſul amongus, and to recall our Ancient Friend Mr. <hi>Baker,</hi> to which we conſent with all our Hearts. And yet, how is it poſſible he can leave us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſees our Fortunate Governour, his intimate Friend, It may be our Governour, when return'd, will ſend to the King of <hi>England</hi> other Letters, and other News, with greater Proofs of his Friendſhip. We expect him in Forty or Fifty Days. And though the Conſul be very earneſt to Embark, we all deſire that he would be pleas'd to ſtay till our Governour's Return. We will have ready at his Service, whatever Ships ſhall be requiſite for him, in caſe there be none that belong to his <hi>Britannic</hi> Majeſty. And perhaps this little ſtay of his, as it may not be unprofitable to us, ſo neither
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98933:12"/>may it be diſ-ſerviceable to your Monarch. This puts us in hope, that our Requeſt will not be diſpleaſing to you, but redound to the Conſternation both of yours and our Enemies. We return you Thanks for defending our Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels againſt the <hi>Hollanders.</hi> We acknowledge your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and beg of God, that in recompence of your Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, he would afford you his Benediction. The <hi>Dutch</hi> were our Friends, when we were under another Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, till the <hi>French</hi> both kindled and fomented the preſent War. The time will come when we ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new our former Friendſhip, and Brotherly Union, if God bleſſes our good Friend, the King of <hi>England</hi> with Life. War is a ſtrange thing, it cauſes more Vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion than Pleaſure: Yet if the <hi>Hollanders</hi> are in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity with the King of <hi>England,</hi> and deſire to be our Friends, it may ſo fall out, that our Succeſſor will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of their Friendſhip. God grant that the Affection which the King of <hi>England</hi> has for you and us, and which we have for that Prince and you, may be always Cordial, Sincere, and of long Continuance. We recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend you to the Peace of God.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>The Fifteenth Day of the Moon</hi> Mahor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticam, <hi>in the Year 1106.</hi>
                        </date> 
                        <hi>From out Renowned City of</hi> Algiers, <hi>in</hi> Barbary.</dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:98933:13"/>
            <p>Nor were the Calm Words of this Letter, the ſole effect which the wintring of Admiral <hi>Ruſſel</hi> wrought upon the Pyrates of <hi>Barbary;</hi> for upon the 5th of <hi>September</hi> laſt, Mr. <hi>Baker</hi> then Conſul for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation at <hi>Argier,</hi> went from thence in an <hi>Algerine</hi> Man of War for <hi>Tunis,</hi> and being conducted to the Camp of <hi>Shahan Dey,</hi> who then lay before that City, deliver'd to him the Letter from His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain.</hi> Upon which, the <hi>Dey</hi> calling together all the <hi>Tripoline</hi> Officers that were in the Camp, recommended to them the renewing the Peace which they had with the King of <hi>England;</hi> and having written to the ſame Effect, to the <hi>Dey</hi> of <hi>Tripoli,</hi> order'd a Man of War to carry Mr. <hi>Baker</hi> thither, where he was not only welcom'd with a Reception, but eaſily obtain'd his Deſires, which ended in a Confirmation of Peace with the Governour of that Place, much to the Advantage of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, and as much to the Diſappointment of the <hi>French,</hi> who endeavour'd all they could to prevent it. Though others ſay, it was Mr <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dington</hi> who reviv'd that Pacification.</p>
            <p>The 31th of <hi>December</hi> arriv'd at <hi>Cadiz,</hi> under the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy of the <hi>Rupert,</hi> and ſeveral other Men of War, the Store-Ships and Victuallers that ſet Sail from the <hi>Spit-Head,</hi> the 5th of the ſame Month.</p>
            <p>Upon the 26th of <hi>December,</hi> Ten <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men of War ſet ſail from <hi>Cadiz,</hi> to cruiſe about the Coaſt of <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal;</hi> and Three Davs after, a <hi>Dutch</hi> Privateer carried into <hi>Cadiz,</hi> a <hi>French</hi> Prize, which he had taken in the Mouth of the <hi>Streights,</hi> and ſent it away for <hi>England,</hi> under a Convoy bound thither, with ſeveral Merchant Men.</p>
            <p>Letters alſo from <hi>Madrid</hi> of the Sixth of <hi>January,</hi> New Stile, gave an account that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Frigates cruiſing in the <hi>Streights,</hi> had taken and ſent to <hi>Cadiz,</hi> Two Ships belonging to <hi>Genoa,</hi> as they ſaid, but bound for ſeveral Ports of <hi>France,</hi> and richly laden.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:98933:13"/>
            <p>Soon after, a <hi>French</hi> Man of War ſailing out of the River of <hi>Lisbon,</hi> with Two Merchant Men under her Convoy, Homeward bound, was taken by one of the Men of War, which Admiral <hi>Ruſſel</hi> had ſent to cruiſe upon the Coaſt of <hi>Portugal;</hi> and the Two Merchant Men had run the ſame Fate, had they not eſcaped by the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the Night. The Captain of the <hi>French</hi> Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, whoſe Name was Monſieur <hi>De la Rochefueille,</hi> was afterwards ſet Aſhore at <hi>Caſcons,</hi> together with all his Men, to the number of Three Hundred. Nor was it long after, before Three <hi>Zeland</hi> Privateers carried into <hi>Cadiz,</hi> a <hi>Dunkirk</hi> Caper of Twenty Guns.</p>
            <p>Toward the beginning of <hi>March,</hi> arriv'd at <hi>Whitehal</hi> the News of an Engagement between Capt. <hi>Killegrew,</hi> and certain <hi>French</hi> Men of War in the <hi>Mediterranean.</hi> The Relations were imperfect at firſt, That Capt. <hi>Killegrew</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving with him a Squadron of Seven <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men of War, ſent away. Three of them to cruiſe in the Channel of <hi>Malta,</hi> and Three about Cape <hi>Peſſaro,</hi> while he remain'd with his ſingle Ship in the <hi>Fare</hi> of <hi>Meſſina;</hi> that quickly after Capt. <hi>Killegrew</hi> fell in with Two <hi>French</hi> Men of War, one of Sixty, the other of Fifty Guns, and engag'd them both for the ſpace of Four Hours; at what time upon the Report of the Guns, one of the Men of War that had been ſent away to cruiſe, came into his Aſſiſtance, and ſo well ſeconded Captain <hi>Killegrew,</hi> that the <hi>French</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took themſelves to a running Fight, and that in a ſhort time after, the Ship of Fifty Guns ſurrendred, but ſoon after ſunk; and that the other having all her Maſts ſhot by the Board, yielded alſo, and was carried to <hi>Meſſina.</hi> This Relation likewiſe gave an Account, that there were Seven Hundred Men Aboard the Two <hi>French</hi> Men of War, the one half of which were Kill'd and Wounded, and that Capt. <hi>Killegrew</hi> was kill'd in the Fight, and about Fifty of his Men Kill'd and Wounded.</p>
            <p>In the mean time other Letters from <hi>Madrid,</hi> of the Ninth of <hi>February,</hi> New Stile, gave an Account that his Majeſties Ship the <hi>Plimouth,</hi> was ſail'd up the <hi>Streights</hi> to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98933:14"/>Cruiſe, but ſaid nothing of this Fight. The ſame Letters alſo farther added, that upon the Firſt of <hi>January,</hi> the <hi>De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſord</hi> Man of War returned to <hi>Cadiz</hi> from Cruiſing, and brought in with her, Two Veſſels of <hi>Genoa,</hi> to be ſearch'd, and Two <hi>French</hi> Prizes, the one a Ship of Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Guns bound from <hi>Marſeilles</hi> to St. <hi>Malo</hi>'s, and the other a Brigantine of the ſame Place, bound to <hi>Marteni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go;</hi> and moreover, that the great Ships were then Careen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>Soon after, came other Letters from <hi>Madrid,</hi> dated <hi>Feb.</hi> 17th, giving an Account that Two <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men of War were arrived at <hi>Bilboa,</hi> who had taken a <hi>French</hi> Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vateer of Eighteen Guns belonging to St. <hi>Malo,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ship bound Home from <hi>Virginia.</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Letters alſo of the 23d of <hi>February,</hi> gaye notice, that the Men of War and Merchants Veſſels which were laden with Proviſions and Stores for the Fleet, and which ſet ſail from the Spit head about the middle of <hi>January,</hi> were all ſafely arriv'd at <hi>Cadiz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But upon the 11th of <hi>March,</hi> was publiſhed a more ample Relation of the Engagement of Captain <hi>Killegrew,</hi> and the Two <hi>French</hi> Men of War; giving an Account, that upon the 20 of <hi>February,</hi> a <hi>Venetian</hi> Ship arriving at <hi>Leghorn,</hi> from the Coaſt of <hi>Sicily,</hi> brought in News of an Engagement in the Channel of <hi>Malta,</hi> between ſome <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and Two <hi>French</hi> Men of War, and that the Two latter were taken: Which was alſo confirm'd by a Bark that arriv'd at the ſame Port, in Eight days from <hi>Meſſina,</hi> with the ſollowing Circumſtances.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Plimouth, Carliſle, Newcaſtle, Southampton, Falmouth</hi> and <hi>Adventure</hi> Frigates, the Firſt being a Third Rate of Sixty Two Guns, and all the reſt Fourth Rates, cruiſing very near the Iſland of <hi>Pantalaria,</hi> upon the 28th of the laſt Month, early in the Morning, diſcovered Two <hi>French</hi> Men of War, one of Seventy Guns, named the <hi>Content,</hi> commanded by the Marquis <hi>de Chalard;</hi> the other call'd the <hi>Trident,</hi> of Sixty Guns, commanded by the Count <hi>D' Anoy,</hi> who ſuppoſing the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Frigates to be Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98933:14"/>Men, bore up towards them; but finding their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, bore away again: Upon which the <hi>Engliſh</hi> made all the Sail they could after them; ſo that it was Four in the Afternoon before the <hi>Plimouth,</hi> commanded by Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Killegrew</hi> could come up with them; and the Wind being then Calm, ſhe along engag'd the <hi>French</hi> Ships for the ſpace of more than an Hour; in which time Captain <hi>Kill grew</hi> was kill'd with a Cannon Shoe. Then came up the <hi>Falmouth,</hi> Captain <hi>Grantham</hi> Commander, who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd them for near another Hour, till the other Four <hi>Engliſh</hi> Frigates came in. Upon which the <hi>French</hi> ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated; the <hi>Carliſle, Newcaſtle</hi> and <hi>Southampton,</hi> purſued the biggeſt of them, and the <hi>Falmouth</hi> and <hi>Adventure</hi> the le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; the <hi>Plimouth</hi> being forced to bear away for <hi>Meſſina,</hi> having loſt her Foretop Maſt, and her other Maſts and Rigging being very much ſhatter'd. As for the <hi>French</hi> they made a Running Fight of it the Night following, and part of the next Day; when their Ships being very much ſhatter'd, and the Count <hi>D' Anoy,</hi> one of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, with many of their Men Kill'd, they both yielded. The <hi>Trident</hi> being Leaky, and the Wind blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very freſh, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſent her to <hi>Gorgonti,</hi> and carried the <hi>Content</hi> to <hi>Meſſina,</hi> where they arrived the 2d of <hi>March.</hi> The <hi>Plimouth</hi> had Fourteen Men Kill'd, and Thirty Wounded. Captain <hi>Kill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>grew</hi> was buried <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and the <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſle, Newcaſtle</hi> and <hi>Southam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitted, put to Sea again the 15th, having notice, as it was ſaid, that Two other Frigates were cruiſing near <hi>Sicily:</hi> At the ſame time alſo the <hi>Plimouth</hi> and <hi>Falmouth</hi> were reſitting, together with the Prize. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Conful at <hi>Meſſina,</hi> ſent away the Marqueſs of <hi>Chalard,</hi> and the greateſt part of the <hi>French</hi> Priſoners, being about Five Hundred and Fifteen, in Two <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Barks, and a <hi>Mall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Ship for <hi>Leghoun,</hi> with a Months Proviſion.</p>
            <p>Some time after theſe Relations had been Printed in <hi>England,</hi> came another Relation from <hi>France,</hi> written by the Count <hi>De Chalard</hi> himſelf, wherein the Count would
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98933:15"/>ſeem to be very particular; though he ſtrains hard to give as much honour as is poſſible for him to do to his own Countrey men.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>AN ABSTRACT OF A LETTER FROM THE <hi>Count de Chalard,</hi> TO THE French Court.</head>
                  <p>UPon the 28th of <hi>January, (ſays he,)</hi> early in the Morning, we diſcovered Six Sail, which we judged to be <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By Two a Clock in the Afternoon, we were joyn'd by a Veſſel, which as we judg'd, carried about Six Guns, which came up within Pistol Shot before ſhe fir'd a Gun. The <hi>Trident</hi> and I fought her for ſome time, but ſhe being ſoon after join'd by ſome others that were the moſt nimble Saylers of her Squadron, the <hi>Trident</hi>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:98933:15"/>divided her Fire, while I ply'd the firſt Veſſel altoge ther till Night came on; at what time my Adverſary having loſt one of her Maſts, kept off; but then I was attack'd by another Veſſel, which left the <hi>Trident,</hi> to fall upon me.</p>
                  <p>All this while the <hi>Trident</hi> fought with great Violence, ſuffering ſeveral Diſcharges from thoſe that came toward the <hi>Content;</hi> but ſhe loſt one of her Maſts a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Night came on: After which I ſaw no more of her. In the Condition that I was, I ſail'd toward the Iſle of <hi>Maretimo,</hi> being continually chas'd by Three Ships, of which one was as big as the <hi>Content,</hi> which joyn'd me about Seven at Night, and fought me about Two Hours, and very much diſabl'd me. However I continued my courſe as well as I could.</p>
                  <p>The next Day in the Morning, I was rejoyn'd by the Ship that fought me the Evening before, which was follow'd by Two more; ſo that by Ten a Clock in the Morning I loſt my Main Maſt.</p>
                  <p>The Enemy purſu'd their Advantage, and in the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon cut down my Mizon, and all the reſt of my Maſts; ſo that the great Ship play'd upon me as ſhe pleas'd her ſelf; for we had neither Helm nor Sails left to govern our Ship. For which reaſon, finding my ſelf in this piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful condition, I call'd the Officers together to have their Advice, who all teſtified their willingneſs to ſacrifice their Lives for the King's Service; but conſidering the Condition of the Ship, and the Superior Number of the Enemy, it was reſolv'd that we ſhould yield, which was done the 29th, at Four in the Afternoon.</p>
                  <p>The Officers and the Marine Guards, behav'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with extraordinary Courage and Bravery.</p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:98933:16"/>
                  <p>After we had yielded, we were put Aboard the <hi>Carliſle;</hi> by the Captain of which Veſſel we were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly well uſed; nor did they take away our Swords, which was done out of a particular eſteem which they had for my Perſon.</p>
                  <p>We were carried to <hi>Meſſina,</hi> where we met the other <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men of War, and the Officers of the <hi>Trident,</hi> which far'd no better than we did, though the Officers and Souldiers behav'd themſelves with all the Bravery imaginable. And the next day that we arrived in the Port, the Governour of <hi>Meſſina</hi> ſent us a Civil Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliment, offering to ſerve us to the utmoſt of his Power, and order'd us to want for nothing. <hi>This Letter was ſubſcrib'd</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>CHALARD.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Upon the 8th of <hi>March,</hi> Five <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and Four <hi>Dutch</hi> Men of War, ſail'd away from <hi>Cadiz,</hi> to meet the Home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bound <hi>Turky</hi> Ships, and the <hi>Mary, Canterbury, Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon,</hi> and <hi>Mury Galley</hi> returned from Cruiſing. And much about the ſame time Rear Admiral <hi>Nevil</hi> was going out with another Squadron of <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Men of War.</p>
            <p>Toward the beginning of <hi>April,</hi> the <hi>Portſmouth, Grey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hound</hi> and <hi>Lark</hi> returned from Cruiſing, having been as far as <hi>Toulon,</hi> where they took a fiſher Boat with Six Men, who confirm'd what had been reported before, that the <hi>French</hi> had no deſign to fit out their Fleet at <hi>Toulon,</hi> but that they were Fortiſying the Town and the Haven, to ſecure it againſt the Aſſaults of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch:</hi> More-eſpecially, that they were at work to Cleanſe and Fortify a ſmall Port in <hi>Provence,</hi> wherein to lay up their Galleys, as believing they will be more ſafe there, than at <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeilles.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:98933:16"/>
            <p>On the 6th of <hi>April,</hi> Seventeen <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Men of War ſet ſail from <hi>Cadiz,</hi> under the Command of Roar Admiral <hi>Nevil;</hi> but upon the 9th, they were put back by contrary Winds.</p>
            <p>Upon the 18th of <hi>April,</hi> Six <hi>Engliſh</hi> Frigates return'd to <hi>Cadiz,</hi> that ſet ſail from thence ſome time before, having left in the Port of <hi>Meſſina,</hi> the Two <hi>French</hi> Ships of Seventy and Sixty Five Guns, which they took in the Channel of <hi>Malta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the 20th of the ſame Month, Admiral <hi>Ruſſel</hi> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd the whole Fleet to fire their Guns at a Minutes Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance between the Firing of every Gun, as being a Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity due upon the firſt notice of the Queen's Funeral.</p>
            <p>Upon the 22d of <hi>April,</hi> a numerous Fleet of Store-Ships, Victuallers, Bomb-ketches, Tranſport-Ships, and Merchant-Men, making in all Sixty Sail, arriv'd at <hi>Cadiz</hi> from <hi>England,</hi> under a Convoy of ſeveral Men of War, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by Captain <hi>Warren;</hi> and then it was ſaid, that Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral <hi>Ruſſel</hi> would ſpeedily put to Sea with the whole Fleet. 'Tis alſo ſaid, that there is an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Conſul arriv'd at <hi>Rome,</hi> to aſſure that Court, that if the Confederate Fleet came into thoſe Seas, it would not be to do the leaſt Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to the Eccleſiaſtical State; and that he alſo at the ſame time demanded that the ſaid Fleet might have leave to buy Freſh Proviſions at <hi>Civita Vecchia,</hi> in caſe they ſhould ſtand in need of them.</p>
            <p>After this, the Letters of the 4th Inſtant, gave an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, that the Fleet had lain ſeveral Days with their Top ſails looſe, ſo that 'twas generally believ'd they were put to Sea e're this.</p>
            <p>Other Letters alſo from <hi>Coronna,</hi> gave an Account, that Two <hi>Engliſh</hi> Frigates had lately taken a <hi>French</hi> Privateer of Twenty Four Guns off of the Southern Cape; moreover that the <hi>Delaval</hi> had taken a Brigantine of Six Guns, and Seventy Men: And farther, that Captain <hi>Goade</hi> in the <hi>Boyn,</hi> has brought to <hi>Gibraltar,</hi> a Great <hi>French</hi> Ship richly laden, that pretended to be a <hi>Venetian.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:98933:17"/>
            <p>Thus we have accompanied this Magnificent and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable Fleet in all the laſt Summers Expedition, to the great diſappointment of <hi>France,</hi> brought it into Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour during the Winter, and ſeen it ready to put to Sea again. So that if the <hi>French</hi> have not made <hi>Toulon</hi> and <hi>Marſeilles</hi> Inacceſſible to Fire and Flames, and Impenetrable to the Batteries of Marine Thunder, it may be expected, and, we doubt not, but to give a more pleaſing Relation of the Actions of this Summer, and fuller of Variety in the next Account.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
